Guillermo Ortiz-Jiménez



in es.linkedin.com/in/gortizji/en

gortizji

@gortizji

gortizji.github.io





About me

I am a **PhD student at EPFL** working under the supervision of Prof. Pascal Frossard. My current research focuses on **understanding deep learning** by studying the complex interactions between datasets, architectures and optimization. My work provides a **novel framework** to design more reliable neural networks that are **robust to adversarial perturbations** and all sorts of **natural distribution shifts**.

Education

Nov 2018 - (Nov 2023) PhD. Electrical Engineering

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, EPFL (Switzerland)

Sep 2016 - Aug 2018 MSc. Electrical Engineering (Best graduate)

Delft University of Technology, TU Delft (Netherlands)

Sep 2011 - Jun 2015 BSc. Telecommunications Engineering (Best graduate)

Universidad Politécnica de Madrid, UPM (Spain)

Research experience

Doctoral assistant at EPFI

Nov 2018 - (Nov 2023) Lausanne, Switzerland

Studying the **inductive bias** of deep learning and how it affects its generalization and robustness properties. My research has already provided insights to improve **adversarial defenses**, **out-of-distribution generalization**, and to understand the **role of architecture in deep learning**.

Master thesis at TU Delft.

Nov 2017 - Aug 2018 Delft, Netherlands

Introduced a novel algorithm based on submodular optimization to sample tensor data and reconstruct it with near-optimal guarantees. Applications to point cloud compression and recommender systems.

Research Intern at Philips Healthcare Research

Jul 2017 - Oct 2017 Hamburg, Germany

Developed self-supervised deep learning algorithms for representation learning and medical image reconstruction of fetal ultrasounds and CT scans.

Research Assistant at Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

Jul 2015 - Jul 2016 Madrid, Spain

Pioneered the use of 3D rendering techniques from computer graphics to simulate radar scattering from the human skin at the THz band.

Software skills

DL frameworks: PyTorch, Tensorflow, JAX. **Languages:** Python, C, Java, Matlab, Javascript.

Misc: Git, Linux, LaTeX, Illustrator, InDesign.

Languages

Spanish: •••• English: ••••

German: •••• French: •••

Dutch: • • • • • •

Awards

2018 National Award for Excellence in Academic Performance by Government of Spain

2018 **Best graduate** by TU Delft (~1000 students)

2016 "La Caixa" Postgraduate Fellowship by La Caixa Foundation (~45,000\$)

2015 Best graduate by Universidad Politecnica de Madrid (~800 students)

Other competitive grants (~18,000\$)

Featured publications

GOJ, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. "Neural Anisotropy Directions". In Advances of Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2020), December 2020

GOJ, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. "Hold me tight! Influence of discriminative features on deep network boundaries". In Advances of Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2020), December 2020

GOJ, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. "Optimism in the face of adversity: Understanding and improving deep learning through adversarial robustness". *Proceedings of the IEEE (Under review)*, October 2020

GOJ, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. "Redundant features can hurt robustness to distribution shifts". In *Uncertainty & Robustness in Deep Learning Workshop (ICML 2020)*, July 2020

C. Vignac, GOJ, and P. Frossard. "On the choice of graph neural network architectures". In IEEE International Conference in Audio, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP 2020), May 2020

GOJ, M. El Gheche, E. Simou and P. Frossard. "Forward-backward splitting for optimal transport based problems". In IEEE International Conference in Audio, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP 2020), May 2020

GOJ, M. El Gheche, E. Simou and P. Frossard. "CDOT: Continuous domain adaptation using optimal transport". In Optimal Transport Workshop (NeurlPS 2019), December 2019

GOJ, M. Coutino, S.P. Chepuri and G. Leus. **"Sparse sampling for inverse problems with tensors"**. *IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing*, June 2019

Student supervision

Itamar Salazar Franco (Graduate intern), Adversarial Robustness and NADs, Fall 2020 Mariam Hakobyam (Semester project), On the role of architecture on NADs, Fall 2020 Maja Stamenkovic (Semester project), Transferring inductive biases, Fall 2020 Johannes Ruether (MSc. Thesis), On the geometry of adversarial robustness, Spring 2020 Julien Heitmann (Semester project), Weight subspace dynamics, Fall 2019 Manuel Faysse (Semester project), Time-varying graph neural networks, Fall 2019

Teaching experience

Machine learning (MSc. course)
A network tour of data science (MSc. course)
Computational optimal transport (PhD. course)

Personal interests

Climbing, running, hiking, skiing, cooking and photography.